Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is כף, chaf, מכות
Makkot 20, we pick up on יט עמוד ב, yud tet amud
bet, four lines down in the wide lines, or actually three lines
down in the wide lines, אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rav Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan, and we're dealing with a list of
things you get מלקות malkos for in the משנה, mishna, and these
are specifically relating to like מעשר שני maaser sheni that you eat
outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קדשים קלים kodashim kalim that you eat outside
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and so on. So the גמרא Gemara just had
some interesting questions about מעשר שני maaser sheni and now we are
going to continue with that focus. So אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מעשר שני מאימתי חייבין עליו?
maaser sheni me'imatai chayavin alav? When are you חייב chayav for מעשר
שני maaser sheni for eating it out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So of
course what do you mean? When you eat it out of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. But no, the חידוש chiddush is that that's not true. It's
not if you just take your designate your מעשר שני maaser sheni
from your fruit and then you eat it.
Why, what is, when would you be חייב? chayav?
משיוראה פני החומה. misheyira pnei hachomah. It would have to first be
brought in and see the inside of the walls, enter into ירושלים
Yerushalayim and then be taken out and eaten outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
but otherwise you do not get the מלקות. malkos. You're still pass
an עשה, aseh, but you don't get the מלקות malkos if you
did not bring it in and then eat it, take it out
again and eat it outside. מאי טעמא? mai taama? Let's read the
פסוק, pasuk, דאמר קרא לפני ה׳ אלהיך תאכלנו. de'amar kra lifnei Hashem
Elokecha tochalennu. You should eat it before Hashem your God,
וכתיב לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך, vechtiv lo tuchal le'echol bish'arecha, you cannot
eat in your gates, מעשר דגנך תירושך ויצהרך, maaser deganecha tiroshcha veyitzharecha,
that's the לא תעשה. lo taaseh. כל היכא
דקרינא ביה לפני ה׳ אלהיך תאכלנו, kol heicha dekarina bei lifnei Hashem
Elokecha tochalennu, once it was in a state where it could be
eaten, it was fit to be eaten לפני ה׳ אלהיך, lifnei Hashem
Elokecha, it was brought into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, then it's in that context
where the תורה Torah is telling you you have to eat this
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's now it's telling you don't eat it בשעריך.
bish'arecha. Okay, קרינא ביה לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך. karina bei lo tuchal
le'echol bish'arecha. וכל היכא דלא קרינא ביה לפני ה׳ אלהיך תאכלנו, vechol
heicha dela karina bei lifnei Hashem Elokecha tochalennu, but if it never
got to the stage where it could be eaten yet, לא קרינא
ביה לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך, lo karina bei lo tuchal le'echol bish'arecha,
you would not apply the לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך lo tuchal le'echol
bish'arecha לא תעשה. lo taaseh. There'd be a מצוות עשה, mitzvat aseh,
לפני ה׳ אלהיך תאכלנו, lifnei Hashem Elokecha tochalennu, but you would not
get the מלקות malkos for the לא תעשה. lo taaseh. And obviously
you don't have to read the פסוק pasuk that way. Bring it
up to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, don't eat it while it's
still in your שעריך. she'arecha. But you also do understand the logic
here because most of the things that have to be eaten in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's cause they start in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קדשים קלים, kodashim
kalim, right, it gets its status in ירושלים Yerushalayim and the problem
is now you're taking it out and you're eating it outside.
So this also would have to sort of be fit to be
eaten and then eaten outside.
Okay, מתיב, metiv, a challenge. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, כהן
שעלה בידו תאנה של טבל, kohen she'alah beyado te'enah shel tevel, if
a כהן kohen had a
fig of טבל, tevel, this is from a תוספתא, Tosefta, ואמר תאנה
זו תרומתה בקצה, ve'amar te'enah zu terumatah beketzah, so I'm being מפריש,
mafrish, I'm designating the very bottom part, like one percent at the
bottom right by the twig part of it to be תרומה, terumah,
and then he'll be allowed to eat תרומה terumah because he can't
eat טבל, tevel, but once he's מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah he can
eat the whole thing, he can eat the תרומה terumah part of
it. מעשר ראשון בצפונה, maaser rishon bitzfonah, the northern part of this
fig is מעשר ראשון. maaser rishon. And then he's going to have
to take תרומת מעשר terumat maaser from the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon
or otherwise the whole thing is the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon is
still טבל. tevel. ומעשר שני
בדרומה, u'maaser sheni bidromah, and מעשר שני maaser sheni is at the
south of it. והיא שנת מעשר שני ובירושלים, vehi shnat maaser sheni
u'viYerushalayim, and it is a
מעשר שני maaser sheni year and he happens to be in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. או מעשר עני ובגבולין, o maaser ani u'vigvulin, or it's
מעשר עני maaser ani and he's outside of the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. אכלה לוקה אחת, achlah lokeh achat, if he would go ahead
and eat it,
he would get one מלקות. malkos. Why, he was מפריש mafrish everything
and he's in ירושלים Yerushalayim and he's eating מעשר שני maaser sheni
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's the חידוש. chiddush. Even though it looks
like he's doing everything right and he's allowed to eat everything, since
he wasn't מפריש mafrish the תרומת מעשר terumat maaser from the מעשר
ראשון, maaser rishon, it's still טבל tevel and he still gets מלקות
malkos for eating טבל. tevel. וזר שאכלה לוקה שתים, vezar she'achlah lokeh
shtayim, and if a non-כהן kohen were to eat this, he would
get two sets of מלקות malkos also because he is eating the
תרומה. terumah. שאילו
בתחילה אכלה אינו לוקה אלא על אחת,
she'ilu betchilah
achlah eino lokeh ela al achat, and here's the irony: before you
were מפריש mafrish anything, the זר, zar, the non-כהן kohen would have
only gotten one set of מלקות malkos because it's טבל, tevel, but
now that you're מפריש, mafrish, there's both תרומה terumah and the טבל
tevel of מעשר ראשון maaser rishon there. Okay, so now fine, that's
the תוספתא. Tosefta. So what are we going to prove from that?
So let's take a look. טעמא דאיתא בירושלים, taama de'itah biYerushalayim, the
reason top of כף עמוד א, chaf amud aleph, the reason the
איתא בירושלים, itah biYerushalayim, he happens to be in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
that's why he's not getting the מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני,
maaser sheni, right, that's how it set it up that there was
only the מלקות malkos for the תרומת מעשר. terumat maaser.
הא בגבולין לוקה שלש, ha bigvulin lokeh shalosh, the implication would be
that if it were outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim and it was מעשר
שני, maaser sheni, he would get מלקות. malkos. For the מעשר שני,
maaser sheini, so that would be two מלקות malkos for the כהן
kohen or three for the ישראל, yisrael, and that definitely is the
implication. And so you see now, that implies that אף על גב
דלאו af al gav d'lav רואי פני חומה, roei pnei choma, that
even though it never made it into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so, you know,
if it's מעשר שני maaser sheini עד ירושלים, ad Yerushalayim, you get
מלקות. malkos. That certainly has been the פשט pshat of the משנה,
mishna, now it's the פשט pshat of this ברייתא. braisa. So the
גמרא gemara says דעייל ואפקי, d'oil v'afkei, gives a very weak אוקימתא
ukiimta answer. It says, no, the ברייתא braisa is talking about a
case that he brought it into ירושלים Yerushalayim and then brought it
back out. And that's why he's getting, you know, and in that
case,
excuse me, what I mean is like the case that it's coming
to to give an exception to like exclude, you know, is a
case where he was in ירושלים Yerushalayim and he brought it out.
Meaning the ברייתא braisa is saying he's in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so he's
not going to get מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני. maaser sheini.
Okay, the implication being not if it started out he would get
מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני, maaser sheini, but the implication being
that
if he started in ירושלים Yerushalayim and then went out, then he
would also be getting, then he would also get another set of
מלקות. malkos. So the גמרא gemara says אי הכי מאי למימרא, ee
hachi mai l'meimra, so then what's the חידוש? chiddush? If you're saying
that the implication is that if it was never in ירושלים Yerushalayim
he gets מלקות, malkos, right, that's the simple implication of the ברייתא,
braisa, that if this whole thing happened to be totally out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim he would get מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני, maaser
sheini, then that's already a חידוש chiddush against what we're trying to
say that it has to be go inside and taken out. But
if you're saying it only means to imply that if he would
have now from ירושלים Yerushalayim bring it out he would get מלקות,
malkos, so then this whole thing is like obvious, there's no חידוש
chiddush in this ברייתא braisa at all, in this תוספתא tosefta at
all. No, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דעיילינהו בטיבליהו דקסבר מתנות שלא הורמו
כמי שהורמו דמיין. hocha b'mai askinan kegon d'oiliuhu bitveilaihu d'kasavar matnos shelo
hurmu k'mi shehurmu damyan. Okay, the חידוש chiddush here is is that
the scenario is you would have brought it in, you know, you
had your fig, you brought it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you weren't מפריש
mafrish yet. And so now it's saying the following: if you're מפריש
mafrish in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you're going to eat the whole thing,
whatever, you know, if you're a כהן kohen you get one set
of מלקות malkos and if you're a ישראל yisrael you get two,
but nobody's getting מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני maaser sheini because
you were מפריש mafrish it and you're in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. However, if,
not if you started outside, but if after you brought the fig
in ירושלים Yerushalayim and before you were מפריש mafrish it you went
back outside and you were מפריש mafrish it then, then you would
also get another set of מלקות malkos for the מעשר שני. maaser
sheini. Okay, and that's already a חידוש, chiddush, assuming there's a requirement
for the מעשר שני maaser sheini that it be brought in and
brought out. The חידוש chiddush is that even though it was only
brought in in its טבל tevel state, the fig was brought in
before any הפרשה hafrasha was done and then it was brought out,
since the מעשר שני maaser sheini had, you know, was going to
be separated from this fig, it is like the מעשר שני maaser
sheini of the fig was brought in ירושלים Yerushalayim and now you
will be חייב. chayav. Okay, וקסבר מתנות שלא הורמו כמי שהורמו דמיין,
v'kasavar matnos shelo hurmu k'mi shehurmu damyan, that the gifts that have
not yet been separated
off are like they are already separated off. Okay, so that's what
this ברייתא braisa is saying: you brought the fig in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
you did this הפרשה, hafrasha, you'll get one מלקות malkos for כהן,
kohen, two for ישראל, yisrael, but the מעשר שני maaser sheini no,
because you're in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But had you brought the fig in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and then brought it back out and then were מפריש,
mafrish, then you would also get מלקות malkos for מעשר שני maaser
sheini because it's like the מעשר שני maaser sheini was brought in
and brought out. Okay, now again, that's not at all in the
ברייתא, braisa, but that's at least to say the case that we
were saying, that would be a case you would get מלקות malkos
for that fits our idea that it needs to be brought in
and brought out, and that there's also a חידוש chiddush that being
brought in in its טבל tevel state is considered being brought in.
So now the גמרא gemara says like this: וסבר רבי יוסי מתנות
שלא הורמו כמי שהורמו דמי, v'savar rabbi yosi matnos shelo hurmu k'mi
shehurmu dami, is this really true? Because this ברייתא, braisa, this תוספתא,
tosefta, was רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. So does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
really hold that something before it's separated it has a like we
sort of already see it there, what's there in potential we already
see it as though it's there? And again, not that it's as
if it's separated that you're not חייב chayav in טבל, tevel, but
as if we sort of see the thing already present. והתניא רבי
שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי יוסי, v'hatanya rabbi shimon ben yehuda
omer mishum rabbi yosi, we have a ברייתא, braisa, רבי שמעון בן
יהודה, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda, or תנן, tnan, a משנה mishna says
in the name of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, לא נחלקו בית שמאי
ובית הלל על פירות שלא נגמרה מלאכתן ועברו בירושלים שיפטרו מעשר שני
שלהם ויאכלו בכל מקום. lo necheleku beis shammai beis hillel al peiros
shelo nigmera melachtan v'avru b'yerushalayim sheyifteru maaser sheini shelahem v'yochlu b'chol makom.
So,
so one of the things also that affect like קליטת מחיצות, klitas
mechitzos, and we've discussed this before, and bringing מעשר שני maaser sheini
into ירושלים Yerushalayim is that once it's brought into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
can no longer be פודה podeh it even if you brought it
back out. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi here is saying, we're going
to see in a minute that there's a debate בית הלל Beis
Hillel בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but nobody debates if the מעשר שני
maaser sheini was brought in before the גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, you
know, the fruit or it's not even מעשר שני maaser sheini yet.
You know, you've got your fruit and you haven't yet finished, if
it's like grain you haven't smoothed over the pile of grain, whatever
it is, you haven't finished the processing of of the. of the
grain, of the produce, and so it's not yet חייב chayav in
מעשר, maaser, and then you bring it in ירושלים Yerushalayim and then
you bring it out, so in that type of a case everybody
agrees it's not like it was brought into ירושלים Yerushalayim and everybody
agrees once you separate מעשר שני Maaser Sheini you can still redeem
it. So that they did not argue. אשכחתה מעשר שני שלהם יאכל
בכל מקום. Ashkachtah Maaser Sheini shelahem yeiachel bechol makom. Now, אהיכא נחלקו,
aheicha nechlaku, so what, where was the debate בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? על פירות שנגמרה מלאכתן al peiros shenigmara melachtan
that you actually did finish the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha of this
grain, of this fruit, and now it's חייב chayav in מעשר, maaser,
but it's still טבל. tevel. And what did you do? ועברו בירושלים,
v'avru b'Yerushalayim, and then you brought them into ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So exactly
our case, טבל tevel that is גמר מלאכה gmar melacha that is
brought into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, is it considered like the מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini has been brought in that now when you separate it you'll
no longer be able to redeem it? שבית שמאי אומרים יחזיר מעשר
שני לשם ויאכל בירושלים, sheBeis Shammai omrim yachzir Maaser Sheini l'sham v'yeiachel
b'Yerushalayim, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you're stuck, it's like the
מעשר שני Maaser Sheini was קליטת מחיצות, klitas mechitzos, was brought into
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, now even if you take it back out as טבל
tevel and then you separate מעשר שני Maaser Sheini you cannot redeem
it. מעשר שני Maaser Sheini has already been status affixed by being
inside ירושלים Yerushalayim even in its טבל tevel form. ובית הלל אומרים
יפדה ויאכל בכל מקום, u'Beis Hillel omrim yifdeh v'yeiachel bechol makom, and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says no, you can redeem it once you
take it back out and you separate מעשר שני. Maaser Sheini. So
this seems to be exactly the question of: do you see the
מעשר שני Maaser Sheini there to be defined by being in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and it's בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says yes according to
רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, but בית הלל Beis Hillel says no. So
obviously we would go like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So how could
the case before about the fig, which is רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi,
how could that be the scenario that when you brought it in
as טבל, tevel, it's the status of the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini
got fixed? Doesn't make any sense.
So that's a בית שמאי Beis Shammai position. ואי סלקא דעתך v'ee
salka dach says the גמרא, Gemara, if you were to think מטבלו
שלא הורם כמי שהורם דמיאן metivlo shelo huram kemi shehuram damyan that
in this case of the fig even before you separate out the
טבל, tevel, or in the case of the פירות peiros that were
נגמרה מלאכתן, nigmara melachtan, it's like you already separate the מעשר שני
Maaser Sheini there and then, then you'll get מלקות malkus when you
bring it back out and separate it.
So הרי קלטוהו מחיצות, harei klatuhu mechitzos, so here that could also
define its status for that you can't redeem it when you bring
it back out and separate it. So why would בית הלל Beis
Hillel be lenient if in the case of the fig you would
get מלקות? malkus? So אמר רבה amar Rabbah says רבה, Rabbah, or
רבא Rava some have, מחיצה לאכול דאורייתא, mechitzah l'echol d'Oraisa, we've seen
this before, מחיצה לקלוט דרבנן. mechitzah liklot d'Rabanan.
מן התורה min haTorah this, the idea
that
you have to eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim is obviously מן התורה,
min haTorah, that the מחיצות, mechitzos, the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim are
where you have to eat it. But the idea that the מחיצות
mechitzos define its status that it cannot be redeemed, that's דרבנן. d'Rabanan.
And so, and therefore now there's another way the מחיצות mechitzos define
its status, not just that it can't be redeemed, but that then
you'll get מלקות malkus when you bring it back out. That's still
in the category of מחיצה לאכול, mechitzah l'echol, because remember the reason
you get מלקות malkus only when you bring it in and bring
it out is because then it was fit to be eaten. So
what he's saying is that in, that whether we look at it
as if the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini is there and is defined
by being in ירושלים Yerushalayim when it's in its טבל tevel status
depends on whether the issue is: am I going to get מלקות
malkus or can I redeem it? וכי גזור רבנן כי איתא בעיניה
בטבלו לא
גזור רבנן. v'ki gazur Rabanan ki isa b'einei b'tivlo lo gazur Rabanan.
So for a דאורייתא d'Oraisa הלכה halacha we'll say even before you
separated it, מטבלו שלא הורם כמי שהורם דמי, metivlo shelo huram kemi
shehuram dami, and it's like the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini is there,
and therefore the מעשר שני Maaser Sheini was brought in, now it's
brought out, you eat it, you get מלקות, malkus, because it was
fit to be eaten and it was defined by being there because
we see it as if it was separated even if it was
only there as טבל. tevel. Whereas when it comes to the issue
of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, that you brought
it out and you separate and now you want to redeem it,
since the whole הלכה halacha that you can't redeem it when you
bring it in and bring it out is a דרבנן d'Rabanan הלכה,
halacha, we're going to limit that דרבנן d'Rabanan הלכה halacha to when
it's actually been separated מעשר שני, Maaser Sheini, when it really is
present and not only when it's there in potential form.
So that's how we've answered this and now we have taken this
statement that is not פשט pshat in the משנה Mishna or the
ברייתא baraisa that you only get מלקות malkus if it's been brought
in and brought out and we've said that the חידוש chiddush of
the ברייתא baraisa is that it would apply even if it's brought
in and then brought out in its טבל tevel form and then
separated. But a different הלכה halacha would apply to the question of
whether it can be redeemed if it's been brought in and brought
out in its טבל tevel form. רבינא אמר כגון דנקיט ליה בקניא
ותיפשוט בעא דאמר רב פפא. Ravina amar kegon d'nakit lei bekanya v'sipshot
baei d'amar Rav Papa. Just to have a nice closure on what
we did yesterday, רבינא Ravina says no, the case here that we're
talking about is going back to the case about the original
תוספתא tosefta that says that it, the suggestion is is that if
it were when it says, the כהן kohen separated it out and
he ate it and he gets one set of מלקות, malkus, and
if it's a ישראל Yisrael he gets two sets of מלקות, malkus,
and they're in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
And we said that the initial answer before we got to the
whole טבל tevel and כמי שהורמו kenishhormu answer, the answer was that
the חידוש chiddush that we're coming to say that if in rather
than eating it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, if after you separated it you
brought it back out and you ate it, you would get another
set of מלקות, malkos, and the גמרא Gemara said, "Well, that would
have been obvious." So now we're saying: No, it wouldn't be obvious
because we're talking about a scenario that it wasn't really totally in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It was the case of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. You
know, you are in ירושלים Yerushalayim and it was connected by a
stick and it was actually out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and that's the
case we're contrasting it to. So what does that mean? So the
ברייתא braisa is saying you separated off this fig, you're in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you know, one מלקות malkos for the כהן, Kohen, two for
the ישראל. Yisrael. But if this מעשר שני Maaser Sheni that was
now in ירושלים Yerushalayim had been in and brought out, but in
the following case never really in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the person was in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni was in a bag
outside and it was connected by a stick, if that were the
scenario that would be like it was brought in and then brought
out and then you went out and you ate it, it would
be like it was brought in and brought out, and then you
would be חייב מלקות. chayav malkos. So that's just a way, again,
to say that it would not have been an obvious case, you
know, it would not be פשוט. pashut. All right, end of the
day is we made that assertion that
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni only חייב chayav if you brought in and
brought out, and this whole case with the fig that sounds like
even if it were straight in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, excuse me, never in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you'd get מלקות. malkos. The גמרא Gemara is saying: No,
that's not the scenario. The scenario either is that it was in
and brought out, that that's when you'd get מלקות malkos if it
was in its טבל tevel form, or another way in which it's
saying something that's a חידוש chiddush is if it went in and
went out but not in its טבל tevel form but in this
halfway way about being on the stick, and even that would be
like coming in and then going out and then you would get
מלקות. malkos. But you do not get מלקות malkos if it always
started outside ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, now we will continue with the next
משנה, Mishnah, getting to things that are much more relevant to us.
הקורח קרחה בראשו, hakoreiach karcha berosho, if somebody makes a bald spot
on his head for, you know, in mourning over a dead body.
לא יקחו קרחה בראשם ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו. lo yikchu karcha berosham
ufeas zkanam lo yigaleichu. Okay, so והמקיף פאת ראשו, vehamakif peas rosho,
and somebody that cuts off, you know, in circles, whatever, the corners
of his head, we'll see a whole major discussion about what that
means. You know, for us we generally take that to mean like
you don't cut your sideburns,
but one reading, first of all, of רש"י Rashi is that you're
only really חייב chayav if you completely do what's it called, like
a tonsure what they, the, you know, the monks had, like you
completely do a circle around your head and cut off all the
hair, you know, that sort of falls below the hairline all around
all around your head, you make like a circle type of a
thing. והמקיף פאת ראשו והמשחית פאת זקנו, vehamakif peas rosho vehamashchis peas
zkano, and if somebody goes ahead and destroys the corners of his
beard, and, you know, the different language of מקיף makif and משחית
mashchis is going to be both, it's echoing the פסוקים, pesukim, and
there'll be practical differences because the reason we use a shaver,
can use a shaver on our beard but not on our פאות,
peyos, sideburns, you know, for men, is because השחתה hashchasa by the
beard, לא תשחית את פאת זקנך, lo sashchis es peas zkanacha,
is understood to be something that like is really like, the way
the גמרא Gemara understands it is it's תער. taar. It's a razor
blade. It's totally completely destroyed, totally cut exactly against the skin. And
something that is a shaver that operates in a scissor motion, even
though because the way a shaver works is that the hairs go
through the shield and then the blade cuts it, so it works
like a scissors that one blade is holding and one is cutting,
even though it gets very close to the skin, that's what the
גמרא Gemara calls מספרים כעין תער, misparayim ke-ein taar, that you're still
not חייב chayav for because it says השחתה, hashchasa, and השחתה hashchasa
is only if it's really a תער, taar, really like a straightedge
razor. Whereas by the פאות peyos where it says לא תקיפו, lo
sakifu,
okay, that is even with, you know, scissors is okay, but something
that is מספרים כעין תער, misparayim ke-ein taar, at least it's מחלוקת
ראשונים, machlokes Rishonim, but we assume that that is a problem. All
right, we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. והסורט סריטה אחת
על המת חייב, vehasoreit srita achas al hameis chayav, and if somebody
makes one incision on their skin for a dead body, okay, ושרט
לנפש לא תתנו בבשרכם, ve-saret lanefesh lo sitnu bivsarchem, so also you
get מלקות. malkos. Now סורט סריטה אחת על חמישה מתים, soreit srita
achas al chamisha meisim, if somebody makes one incision for five dead
bodies, like he is doing it for five relatives died God forbid,
and he is doing it in only this one act, but he
is doing it as a way of grieving for all five, so
this is a huge חידוש chiddush that you would think it's one
לאו, lav, but every מת meis makes it defined as it was
a different, it's like you were סורט soreit for that מת meis
and סורט soreit for that מת meis and סורט soreit for that
מת, meis, so even though it's one act you'll get multiple מלקות.
malkos. You know, we've had this before, like eating a type of
bug and you get multiple מלקות. malkos. It's possible to get multiple
מלקות malkos for one act. act, and this is interesting
that it's done for a particular מת meis that can define it
a sort of like as it's you know the מת meis it's
done for gives it its distinct identity. So one act can be
five—get five מלקות. malkos. Oh, חמישה שריטות על מת אחד, chamisha sritos
al meis echad, that's more obvious. Or five separate incisions all for
one dead body, חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achas
ve'achas. You get separate set of lashes. There would have to have
been התראה. hasra'ah. על הראש שתים, אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן. al harosh
shtayim, achas mikan ve'achas mikan. So on the head there is you
know two, you know, corners, one on you know of the sideburns,
one on each side of the head, you know where each of
the sideburns is.
על הזקן al hazakan and for the beard שתים מכאן ושתים מכאן
ואחת מלמטה, shtayim mikan veshtayim mikan ve'achas milmata, two here, one like
on each like the top of the cheek, the bottom of the
cheek, and one at the bottom by the chin. רבי אליעזר אומר
Rabbi Eliezer omer אם נטלו כולן כאחת אינו חייב אלא אחת. im
nitlu kulan ke'achas eino chayav ela achas. So Rabbi Eliezer said
if you basically went ahead and did like one shaving and shaved
it all off at once, you would only get one set of
מלקות. malkos.
You
know so the simple sense is that according to the חכמים chachamim
here, even if you you know person did it in one full
act, there are five separate איסורים. issurim. Each פאה, pe'ah, each corner,
you know the top of the cheek, the bottom of the cheek,
and the chin, is a separate איסור. issur. Assuming that they got
you know you were warned, you got the התראה, hasra'ah, you would
be חייב chayav five. For רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's all basically
one איסור. issur. ואינו חייב עד שיטלנו בתער, ve'eino chayav ad sheyitlenu
beta'ar,
and you're only חייב chayav again by the beard unless you do
it with a straight edge razor. That's what we talked about. רבי
אליעזר אומר אפילו לקטו במלקט או ברהטני חייב. Rabbi Eliezer omer afilu
likto bemelaket o berahitni chayav. Even if you just do it with
a type of a like tweezers, you would also be חייב. chayav.
It does not have to be an act of cutting, it does
not have to be a razor. So we will see all of
this in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. גמרא's Gemara's first going to start with
the bald spot. לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם. lo yikrechu korcha berosham. So
this is what it says in אמור Emor by the כהנים. Kohanim.
Now when the תורה Torah when it speaks about the כהנים, Kohanim,
it doesn't mention don't do it for a dead body. But when
it mentions it for the ישראל, Yisrael, so לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו
קרחה בין עיניכם למת. lo sisgodedu velo sasimu korcha bein eineichem lameis.
Okay,
so what the גמרא's Gemara's going to do is you could have
separated it. You could have said for a normal ישראל Yisrael there's
an איסור issur to do it only for a dead body and
that's also בין עיניכם. bein eineichem. By the way, that's also a
good point that the בין עיניכם bein eineichem by the תפילין tefillin
does not literally mean between the eyes because you can't make a
bald spot between your eyes. There's no hair literally between your eyes.
Okay, so that part of your head that sort of goes right
between your eyes, the top of your head where your תפילין tefillin
is. So you could have said for a ישראל Yisrael it's לא
תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם למת. lo sasimu korcha bein eineichem lameis. It's
only למת lameis and it's only בין עיניכם. bein eineichem. For the
כהנים Kohanim it's לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם, lo yikrechu korcha berosham, it's
anywhere and it's even not for מת. meis. That's not what the
גמרא Gemara does. The גמרא Gemara puts it all together and says
whether it's כהנים, Kohanim, whether it's for ישראל, Yisrael, it's not limited
to בין עיניים, bein einayim, but it is limited to the למת.
lameis. So it's interesting that it takes the למת lameis part from
the ישראל Yisrael but the בין עיניים bein einayim it does not
take and it assumes anywhere. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן.
tanu rabanan. לא יקרחו. lo yikrechu. יכול אפילו קרח ארבע וחמש קרחות
לא יהיה חייב אלא אחת. yachol afilu kerach arba vechamesh korchos lo
yehei chayav ela achas. Maybe first of all before we even get
to bringing those two different פסוקים psukim in sync, maybe it says
you know maybe each bald spot would just be like more of
the same, it would not be considered a separate act. תלמוד לומר
קרחה לחייב על כל קרחה וקרחה, talmud lomar korcha lechayiv al kol
korcha vekorcha, to say that you're חייב chayav on each one separately.
Okay, so now we'll see about that in a minute because you
know we've dealt whatever the whole question is how does התראה hasra'ah
fit into this, you know, what's the חידוש chiddush here, how would
it apply if somebody was say eating טרף treif food, you know
would they be חייב chayav for every כזית? kezayis? So hold off
on that. Okay, but let's just finish this ברייתא. braisa. וחייב על
כל קרחה וקרחה. vechayav al kol korcha vekorcha. בראשם מה תלמוד לומר?
berosham mah talmud lomar?
What does it mean when it says בראשם, berosham, לא יקרחו קרחה
בראשם? lo yikrechu korcha berosham?
So by the כהנים Kohanim it's anywhere in the head is what
the פסוק pasuk says. לפי שנאמר לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו קרחה בין
עיניכם למת, lefi shene'emar lo sisgodedu velo sasimu korcha bein eineichem lameis,
because by ישראל Yisrael it says בין עיניכם. bein eineichem. יכול לא
יהא חייב אלא על בין עינים בלבד, yachol lo yehei chayav ela
al bein einayim bilvad, maybe only בין עיניים bein einayim for the
ישראל. מניין Yisroel minayin? לרבות כל הראש? kol harosh. תלמוד לומר בראשם
לרבות כל הראש. talmud lomar berosham lerabos kol harosh.
So we take the broader בראשם. berosham. That's so. כל הראש. ואין
לי אלא בכהנים. Vein li ela bakohanim.
Now, maybe that broader, now the גמרא's Gemara recognizing that the פסוקים
pesukim might actually play out differently, you know, the broader איסור issur
for כהנים kohanim and the narrower one for the ישראל. Yisrael. אין
לי אלא בכהנים, Ein li ela bakohanim, maybe it's only by the
כהנים kohanim that it applies to the entire head? בכהנים שריבה בהן
הכתוב מצוות יתירות Bakohanim sheriba bahen hakatuv mitzvos yeseiros
that they have, you know, more demands and more מצוות. mitzvos. ישראל
Yisroel. מניין?
How do I know by ישראל Yisroel that the principle that there's
an איסור issur that applies totally to ראשו, rosho, the complete ראשו
rosho as well? נאמר כאן קרחה ונאמר להלן קרחה, Ne'emar kan karcha
v'ne'emar l'hallan karcha, like גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. By the כהנים kohanim
it says לא יקרחו קרחה lo yikirchu karcha and by the ישראל
Yisroel it's לא תשימו קרחה. lo sasimu karcha. מה להלן חייב על
כל קרחה וקרחה וחייב על הראש כבין עיניים, Mah l'hallan chayav al
kol karcha v'karcha v'chayav al harosh k'vein einayim, the same way that
by the כהנים kohanim I learned out every individual bald spot and
the entire head,
so כבין עיניים, k'vein einayim, אף כאן חייב על כל קרחה וקרחה
וחייב על הראש כבין עיניים. af kan chayav al kol karcha v'karcha
v'chayav al harosh k'vein einayim. Okay? So this is the key, you
know, it's the קרחה קרחה karcha karcha גזירה שוה gezeira shava which
allows me to apply everything from one to the other. And that's
now also going to allow me to apply the limit of על
המת. al hameis. ומה להלן על המת אף כאן על המת. U'mah
l'hallan al hameis af kan al hameis. And the same way that
by ישראל Yisroel it says על המת, al hameis, even by כהנים
kohanim it's על המת, al hameis, it's all one איסור. issur. Now,
it didn't exactly tell me why it said בין עיניים bein einayim
if it was going to אסור assur everything, but, but you know,
but it's an interesting question, like why doesn't it say that like,
well, the פסוק pasuk by the כהנים kohanim doesn't mention על המת,
al hameis, so maybe it would apply even if it's not על
המת. al hameis. So the point is, is that then you can
say בין עיניכם bein eineichem is talking like, you know, like as
an example. It's not meant to limit it, and ראשו rosho tells
you the whole head. So once we're putting everything together, and you
have something that says בראשם berosham and you have something that says
בין עיניכם, bein eineichem, you could say בין עיניכם bein eineichem is
like לאו דווקא lav davka and the בראשם berosham is really what
dictates. But you know, על המת al hameis really describes the nature
of the קרחה karcha that we are describing, and there's nothing that
would explicitly broaden it. It doesn't say what the context is by
the כהנים. kohanim. So we're going to take the בין עיניכם bein
eineichem part, the על המת al hameis part to be sort of,
you know, the one that we're sticking with. So
that's just the ברייתא. Baraisa. Now we're going to analyze each piece.
And the interesting part, and this is sort of also echoed at
the end by the ביאור, Biur, do you get five מלכות, malkos,
do you just get one? You know, how do you define separate
acts for מלכות malkos and how does התראה hasra'ah play into all
of that? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, last line of כ' עמוד א': kaf amud aleph: הני ארבע
וחמש קרחות היכי דמי? Hani arba v'chamesh karchos heichi dami?
This case that if you do four or five, you get four
or five lashes. What's the context of this? אילימא בזה
אחר זה ובחמש התראות פשיטא. Ilima b'zeh achar zeh u'vachamesh hasra'os pshita.
If it is like sequentially, you know, the עדות eidus say don't
make a קרחה על המת, karcha al hameis, and you say אף
על פי כן af al pi chen and you make an incision.
And then they say again don't make a קרחה על המת, karcha
al hameis, and אף על פי כן af al pi chen you
make an incision. So like obviously you don't need a פסוק pasuk
קרחה karcha to tell you you're חייב chayav each one individually. You
did five separate איסורים issurim and they are separated by the different
התראה. hasra'ah. אלא בחד התראה. Ela b'chad hasra'ah.
Okay, so it was only once they said don't make a, you
know, don't make an incision על המת, al hameis, and you said
אף על פי כן af al pi chen and then you made
like five incisions. All right? So, so maybe that's the חידוש chiddush
that you get five מלכות. malkos. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מי חייב? Mi chayav? That would not fit our general principle. והתנן,
Vehatnan, we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: נזיר שהיה שותה יין כל
היום אינו חייב אלא אחת. Nazir shehayah shoseh yayin kol hayom einu
chayav ela achas. If a נזיר Nazir was to drink wine the
entire day, he only gets one set of lashes. אמרו לו אל
תשתה אל תשתה והוא שותה חייב על כל אחת ואחת. Amru lo
al tishteh al tishteh v'hu shoseh chayav al kol achas v'achas. If
they said like don't drink, don't drink and he went ahead, you
know, they gave him התראה hasra'ah each time, then that התראה hasra'ah
would break up the acts and he'd get מלכות malkos separate for
each one. So what this is saying is, is that even if
it's not just saying that if the נזיר Nazir was drinking straight,
even if he drank a gallon, you can only give him one
set of מלכות. malkos. It says like he was שותה כל היום.
shoseh kol hayom. He drank at 9:00 AM, then he took a
break, he took a walk around the, you know, the block, he
watched some TV, then at 10:00 AM he did another drink, then
at 1:00 PM he did a drink, and then at 4:00 PM
he did a drink. Nevertheless, even though those are separate acts of
drinking, the התראה, hasra'ah,
you know, if he didn't get, he only gets one set of
מלכות. malkos. Okay? Because it's sort of like make up your mind.
If it was a continuous act, you know, glug, glug, glug and
he drank a gallon, then even though it was multiple שיעורים, shiurim,
it was one act and he's only going to get one set
of מלכות. malkos. If they are broken up and there's a real
separation between them and he took a walk around the block and
he watched some TV, then the התראה hasra'ah doesn't go on the
other acts. Okay? So basically from this we see that if you
have separate acts, you know... If this breaks between them, you need
separate התראות. hasra'os. You are only going to get מלקות malkos for
the first of the acts. If you have one continuous act and
you're like breaking, the התראה hasra'ah can break up a relatively continuous
act. Okay, but even if your acts are broken already because there's
breaks, you know, if it only has one התראה, hasra'ah, you're only
going to get one set of מלקות. malkos. So the גמרא Gemara
says: Why do I need a פסוק pasuk here by the incisions?
If you're making, you know, incisions, many many incisions, and it's one
התראה, hasra'ah, so then you would only get one מלקות, malkos, you
know, and we don't think that the פסוק pasuk of קרחה karcha
is going to change this הלכה halakha that the התראה hasra'ah only
goes on the act that immediately comes afterwards. So you would only
get one מלקות. malkos. Okay, and if there was a התראה hasra'ah
that preceded it, each separate act, you wouldn't need a special פסוק.
pasuk. So what's going on here? What is the חידוש chidush of
כל קרחה וקרחה? kol karcha v'karcha? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא,
צריכא דשך חמש אצבעותיו
נשא. lo tzricha d'shach chamish etzba'otav nasha. No,
the case is that he put his five fingers into some type
of depilatory, okay, ואצבעינה בבת אחת, v'atzveina b'vas achas,
and he put that straight, you know, on his head. And immediately
in one act, by putting all five fingers in five different places,
he made five bald spots. And in that case, דהוי ליה התראה
לכל חדא וחדא, d'havei leh hasra'ah l'chol chada v'chada, in that case,
the התראה hasra'ah comes right before all each act, okay, because you
have the התראה hasra'ah and then it was one act that made
five bald spots, and that fits our principle. The principle is the
התראה hasra'ah has to be immediately before the act. That was true
here. And the חידוש chidush is because the act consisted of five
different bald spots, so we conceptualized it as five acts or five
different איסורים issurim and you get five מלכיות. malkiyos. Okay, so you
wouldn't be able to have something like that by drinking. What, you're
drinking two sides of your mouth? It's all the same drinking. All
right. So this is a very important principle of how התראה hasra'ah
works and about like something that has a שיעור shiur and a
minimum, and do we consider it one or do we consider it
multiple? If you're doing a continuous act of drinking a gallon of
water, that's one act and only one set of מלקות. malkos. Okay,
if that however is interrupted, I don't know if it's clear that
you have to take a breather between them or not, but if
there's warnings before each, you know, רביעית, revi'is, that makes it multiple
acts, multiple מלקות. malkos. Even if they are separated by space, though,
and they are clearly multiple acts, you will not get multiple מלקות
malkos unless there's a התראה hasra'ah before each one because the התראה
hasra'ah only goes in the immediately following act and you can only
get מלקות malkos for that act. Okay, so the חידוש chidush here
is you can do five spots in one act and you would
get five מלכיות. malkiyos. All right. רב הונא אמר: Rav Huna amar:
Okay, now, וכמה שיעור קרחה? v'kamah shiur karcha? How big is a
bald spot to be חייב? chayav? What's the minimum? רב הונא אמר:
Rav Huna amar: כדי שיראה מראשו. kedei sheyeira merosho.
That it should be, you should be able to see a bald
spot on his head, okay. So I guess, you know, somebody looking
at the top of his head, it doesn't sort of say do
you sort of move away the hair and you can see it
or do you just see it without
even trying to get closer to the scalp? Okay, but it has
to be visible. רבי יוחנן אמר משום אלעזר ברבי שמעון: Rabbi Yochanan
amar mishum Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon: כגריס. k'gris. It has to be the
size of like a lentil bean, okay, and if we go by
the גרסא girsa in the we have in the brackets, תנאי: כמה
שיעור קרחה? כגריס. אחרים אומרים: כדי שיראה מראשו. tanai: kamah shiur karcha?
k'gris. acheirim omrim: kedei sheyeira merosho. We have a debate of תנאים
Tannaim exactly those two opinions. אמר רבי יהודה בר חביבא: Amar Rabbi
Yehuda bar Chaviva: פליגי בה תלתא תנאי. pligi ba tlasa tanai. It's
a three-way debate of תנאים. Tannaim. חד אמר כגריס, chad amar k'gris,
וחד אמר כדי שיראה מראשו, v'chad amar kedei sheyeira merosho, וחד אמר
כשתי שערות, v'chad amar k'shtei searot, just two hairs. Okay, ואיכא דמתו
שתי שערות ומיילי בכיעדשה. v'ika de'masu shtei searot u'mailei b'ki'adasha.
And some take out the two hairs and sort of put in
the
עדשה. adasha. A lentil bean, a lentil, excuse me, I think I
might have said lentil before by גריס, gris, but גריס gris is
actually a type of a bean, some type of a bean. Okay,
so you have a bean, you have two hairs, and you have
a bean, you have visible,
so wait, what are the three again? Let's do that again. One
says כגריס, k'gris, a bean, and one says visible from the head,
and one says two hairs, and some take out the two hairs,
funny, take out the two hairs, and instead say, you know, the
size of a lentil. וסימנך בבהרת כגריס ומחיה בכיעדשה. v'simanch b'bahares k'gris
u'michyah b'ki'adasha.
And the way to remember this is that, you know, by spots
of צרעת tzara'at because now, you know, it's like it's not surprising
that it's similar שיעורים shiurim by these type of things, that the
white spot has to be the size of a גריס, gris, of
this type of a bean to be a problem, and the healing
when it says מחיה, michyah, you know, there's a it heals over
and that's an also relevant to the laws of צרעת, tzara'at, then
that is when it is the size of a עדשה. adasha. All
right, so that those are the sort of the two opinions that
are the sizes that are more like, you know, quotes. quantifiable as
the types of normal שיעורים shiurim given in reference to other things.
And the other two are not ones that you'll forget; the other
two are either the two hairs or you know, visible on the
head. Okay. תנא. tana. הנוטל כמלא פי הזוג בשבת חייב. hanoteil kimlo
pi hazug bashabbat chayav.
If somebody takes, you know, how much hairs do you have to
pluck because there's an איסור issur of גיזה giza of on שבת,
shabbat, so you cut the amount to fill a זוג zug literally
a pair but a scissors, if that's how much you cut for
שבת shabbat then that is the minimum שיעור shiur and you're חייב
מיתה. chayav mita. וכמה מלא פי הזוג vechama mlo pi hazug and
how much is it? אמר רב יהודה amar rav yehuda שתים shtayim
just two hairs. So because it doesn't have to really totally fill
up a scissors, okay, so even two hairs is considered that that
would be a meaningful scissor cut,
you know or maybe it's like just at the edge of the
scissors, you know, just some little snipping,
that's maybe the פי הזוג, pi hazug, you know, the mouth of
it, the opening of it. והתניא vehatanya לקרחה שתים lekorcha shtayim but
one minute, but that ברייתא braita says for שבת shabbas it's it's
the fill of the head of the scissors but for a bald
spot it is two hairs, that's the opinion of two hairs. That
seems like it's different than the amount for שבת. shabbat. So it
says אימא וכן לקרחה שתים. eima vechen lekorcha shtayim. All right, so
modify the ברייתא braita to say, you know, the fill of a
scissors of the tip of a scissors for שבת shabbat and that's
what's considered גיזה, giza, שיעור shiur and also for a bald spot
same שיעור shiur two hairs again, not exactly פשט. pshat. תניא נמי
הכי tanya nami hachi we taught similarly, הנוטל כמלא פי הזוג בשבת
חייב hanoteil kimlo pi hazug bashabbat chayav וכמה מלא פי הזוג vechama
mlo pi hazug שתים. shtayim. Okay, but we have a ברייתא braita
that says that explicitly that does combine the two, how much is
the mouth of a scissors, two hairs. רבי אליעזר אומר אחת. Rabbi
Eliezer omer achat. No, even one hair is enough to be חייב.
chayav. ומודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר במלקט לבנות מתוך שחורות אפילו אחת שהוא
חייב. umodim chachamim lerabbi eliezer bemlaket levanot mitoch shachorot afilu achat shehu
chayav. The the חכמים chachamim agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that if you pick out a white hair from among your black
hairs, you know people do when their hair starts turning white, that
in that case even though quantitatively it's only one hair, qualitatively it
is significant because now it makes all your hair look black, you've
removed this one offensive white hair. So in that case they agree
that even one hair you're חייב chayav for. ודבר זה אפילו בחול
אסור vedavar zeh afilu bechol assur and that's not only אסור assur
on שבת, shabbat, it's also on the weekday משום שנאמר לא ילבש
גבר שמלת אשה mishum shene'emar lo yilbash gever simlat isha a man
cannot wear the clothes of a woman. So it understands that for
a man to be doing this because of course it's just default
assuming we're always talking about a man, for a man to be
doing this would be sort of changing his appearance in a way
that is sort of similar to, you know, how women take care
of their appearance. So that's fascinating that that is included in the
איסור issur of לא ילבש. lo yilbash. It is not clothing, it
is not that the end result is feminine, the end result, you
know, is something like there's a feminine look to him, right, it's
just black hair, but it's but it seems that any type of
a treatment of appearance that is a treatment that is done by
the opposite sex, the way they take care of their appearance so
that they should, you know, look nice, that would be the איסור
issur of שמלת אשה simlat isha or, you know, or שמלת גבר.
simlat gever. So
which is just fascinating in terms of the definition and also gets
to גמרא gemara about looking in a mirror and fixing up your
appearance in a mirror for men is seen as something women do,
but you know nowadays of course ראשונים rishonim say that that is
very culturally contextual and therefore like a lot of that would not
apply nowadays, it really would have to be something that is very
specific, you know, for the other gender. Okay, we will end here.